# Ao LIU

## Ph.D. in Computer Science



## Summary

Research Machine Learning (Recommendation Systems, Learning to Rank, Algorithm Design, etc.),

Interests Differential Privacy, Computational Social Choice, and Quantum Computation

**Experience** 1+ years of industry experience in machine learning (personalized recommendation)

Hands-on experience in recommendation systems, LLM, and theoretical computer science

Academia Published more than 25 papers and received more than 250 citations to date.

Reviewed 50+ papers for top AI conferences or journals.

### Education

01/2018 - 05/2023 **Ph.D. in Computer Science,** Rensselaer Polytechnic Institute (RPI) Troy, NY

Thesis: Group Decision Makings from Partial Preferences [Link]

08/2015 – 05/2018 M.Eng. in Material Physics, Rensselaer Polytechnic Institute (RPI) Troy, NY

08/2010 - 05/2014 B.S. in Mathematics and Physics, Tsinghua University Beijing, China

Minor in Computer Technology, and in Academic Talent Program

## Experience

07/2023 - Present Software Engineer at Google Core ML

Mountain View, CA

Design and Research More Efficient Transformers for Recommendation Systems

05/2022 - 08/2022 Research Intern at Google Core ML Mountain View, CA

Project: A More Accurate Position Bias Estimator for Unbiased Learning to Rank

- $\circ$  Significant accuracy improvement ( $\sim$ 8%) v.s. the sate-of-art without extra computational resources.
  - Proposed a more accurate model for position bias in recommendation systems.
  - Designed a new machine learning framework based on the proposed position bias model and two-tower model. (user-modeling, algorithm design, statistics)
  - Implemented a data pipeline to extract the required features from data. (C/C++)
  - Implemented the machine learning framework, tested on public dataset, and integrated it into Google codebase. (Python, TensorFlow, GoogleTest)

## 07/2016 - 03/2018 Visiting Scholar at MIT-IBM Watson AI Lab

Cambridge, MA

Project: Certifiably Robust Interpretation via Rényi Differential Privacy

- O Significant robustness improvement ( $\sim$ 12%) plus accuracy improvement v.s. the sate-of-art.
  - Yes! we improved both robustness and accuracy at the same time! Note that accuracy and robustness are trade-offs in machine learning.
  - Theoretically connected Rényi differential privacy and interpretation robustness.
  - Designed a new robust algorithm to interpret neural networks for image classifications.
  - Implemented the proposed robust algorithm and tested it on VOC2007 dataset for various properties, including robustness, accuracy, and computational efficiency. (PyTorch, TorchRay, TensorFlow)
- O Delivered one academic paper (on top AI journal) and two patents.

#### Skills

**Implementation** Programming languages: Python, C/C++, MATLAB

Tools and platforms: TensorFlow, PyTorch, TorchRay, LATEX, GoogleTest

**Design/ Theory** User-modeling, Algorithm design, Statistics, Time/Sample-complexity analysis, Markov chain Mount-Carlo (MCMC), Differential privacy analysis, Robustness analysis, Model identifiability.

#### Review Services

Journal Information Sciences, TMLR, ACM ToIS, Sankhya B

Conference NeurIPS (20,21,22&23), ICML (22,23&24), ICLR (23&24), AAAI (21&22), IJCAI-22

| TMLR              | Smoothed Differential Privacy [PDF] <u>Ao Liu</u> , Yu-Xiang Wang, and Lirong Xia   |
|-------------------|---|
| UAI-23            | Accelerating Voting by Quantum Computation [PDF] <u>Ao Liu</u> , Qishen Han, Lirong Xia, and Nengkun Yu   |
| AIJ               | Certifiably Robust Interpretation via Rényi Differential Privacy [Link] [ArXiv] <u>Ao Liu</u> , Xiaoyu Chen, Sijia Liu, Lirong Xia, and Chuang Gan Also in proceedings of AAAI-23 Journal Track (oral presentation) |
| AAAI-23 (oral)    | Differentially Private Condorcet Voting [PDF] Zhechen Li, <u>Ao Liu</u> , Lirong Xia, Yongzhi Cao, and Hanpin Wang  |
| AAAI-22           | The Semi-Random Likelihood of Doctrinal Paradoxes [PDF] $\underline{Ao\ Liu}$ , and Lirong Xia  |
| IJCAI-22 (oral)   | Learning Mixtures of Random Utility Models with Features from Incomplete Preferences [PDF] Zhibing Zhao, <u>Ao Liu</u> , and Lirong Xia   |
| JAIR              | Learning to Design Fair and Private Voting Rules [PDF] Farhad Mohsin, <u>Ao Liu</u> , Pin-Yu Chen, Francesca Rossi, and Lirong Xia  |
| UAI-20 (oral)     | How Private Are Commonly-Used Voting Rules? [PDF] Farhad Mohsin, <u>Ao Liu</u> , Pin-Yu Chen, Francesca Rossi, and Lirong Xia   |
| ETRA-20 Adjunct   | Let It Snow: Adding Pixel Noise to Protect the Users Identity [Link] Brendan John, <u>Ao Liu</u> , Lirong Xia, Sanjeev Koppal, and Eakta Jain   |
| AAAI-19 (oral)    | Near-Neighbor Methods in Random Preference Completion [PDF] <u>Ao Liu</u> , Qiong Wu, Zhenming Liu, and Lirong Xia  |
| AAAI-19 (oral)    | Learning Plackett-Luce Mixture from Partial Preferences [PDF] <u>Ao Liu</u> , Zhibing Zhao, Chao Liao, Pinyan Lu, and Lirong Xia  |
| ETRA-19 (oral)    | Differential Privacy for Eye-Tracking Data [PDF] <u>Ao Liu</u> , L. Xia, A. Duchowski, R. Bailey, K. Holmqvist, and E. Jain   |
| US Patent         | Certifiably Robust Interpretation [PDF] <u>Ao Liu</u> , Sijia Liu, Bo Wu, Lirong Xia, Qi Cheng Li, and Chuang Gan   |
| US Patent         | Interpretation Maps with Guaranteed Robustness [PDF] <u>Ao Liu</u> , Sijia Liu, Abhishek Bhandwaldar, Chuang Gan, Lirong Xia, and Qi Cheng Li   |
|                   | Awards and Teaching   |
| 09/2019 - 05/2022 | RPI-IBM AI Horizon Scholarship 3-year scholarship supported by Rensselaer-IBM Artificial Intelligence Research Collaboration  |
| 09/2016 - 05/2017 | RPI Presidential Graduate Research Fellowship A One-Year Fellowship for Outstanding Graduate Students [Certificate]   |
| Spring 2023       | Teaching Assistant of CSCI 4150: Introduction to AI<br>Instructor: Lirong Xia   |
| 04/2021           | Guest Lecture at CSCI 4967/6967: Economics and Computation<br>Topic: The Semi-Random Likelihood of Doctrinal Paradoxes  |

Spring 2023 Teaching Assistant of MATH 1020: Calculus II

Instructor: David A. Schmidt

Selected Publications